ZOS Unix is made up of a system and application services.
There's a system application programming interface,
or a system API, which is a set of C language functions
and the operating system interfaces that support them.
Some services are also accessible through a simple language.
There are shell and utility interactive interfaces
to ZOS Unix services.
A hierarchical file system is a byte-oriented file system
familiar to Unix programmers,
and DBX, or Debugger for Unix,
is an interactive tool for debugging
C and C++ language applications that use ZOS Unix services.
The picture shown here shows how ZOS Unix,
the shell interface, and the API
relate to the rest of the ZOS operating system.
Here we see the API interface and shell interface
leading into language environments,
which executes the shell and utilities.
BCP is the base control program.
We have multiple file systems here,
hierarchical file system, ZOS file system,
and network file system.
Support is going away for the HFS data structure
used by the ZOS Unix environment,
so you want to migrate your HFS to ZFS
and enjoy the performance gains that come from doing that.
The Unix file system itself is hierarchical
and byte-oriented.
Finding a file in this file system
is done by searching a directory or a series of directories.
There's no concept of like a ZOS catalog
that points directly to a file.
A path name identifies a file
and consists of directory names and a file name.
A fully qualified file name,
which consists of the name of each directory
in the path to a file plus the file name itself
can be up to 1,023 bytes long.
The hierarchical file system allows for file names
in mixed case.
Like Unix, ZOS Unix is case sensitive
to file and directory names.
So for example, in the same directory,
the file my file in uppercase is a different file
than my file in lowercase.
The ZOS Unix shell and utilities
is the interactive interface for users.
It provides a command interface
to the ZOS Unix environment.
A user gets access to the shell
by either logging on to TSOE
or by using the remote login features of TCP IP or login
by using telnet or SSH.
If they use TSOE,
a command called OMVS creates a shell for the user.
The user then works within the shell environment
until exiting or temporarily switching back
to the TSOE environment.
If the user enters ZOS through the R login
or telnet capabilities of TCP IP,
the shell environment is automatically created for them
and they have limited access to TSO services.
The shell is a command interpreter
which accepts commands defined in XPG 4.2 standard.
Some commands call programs called utilities.
The shell user can create named lists
of shell commands called a shell script,
which becomes a path on your command.
The shell provides support to invoke the ISP editor
to edit and browse HFS files for the TSOE user.
For the non-TSOE user,
the VI editor is supported.
Unix system services are included in the ZOS system.
Support is provided for enhanced ASCII functionality.
Enhanced ASCII makes it easier
to port internationalized applications
developed on or for ASCII platforms to ZOS platforms
by providing conversion from ASCII to epsidic
and the other way from epsidic to ASCII.
There's support to make it easier to shut down
and restart the Unix system services environment.
And support is also provided to allow access control lists
or ACLs to be used to control access to Unix files
and directories by individual user IDs and group IDs.
This support provides greater granularity of access
than the existing permission bit support.
And the key point here is what distinguishes ZOS Unix
from other variants is that Unix system services
are integrated into the ZOS base
instead of added as middleware
or shipped as a separate operating system.
And as a result of that,
not only can Unix applications be written
for the IBM Z platform,
they can also take advantage of the ZOS facilities
and IBM Z server hardware
to obtain enterprise level qualities of service.
The ZOS system includes application enablement services
that provide support for object oriented technology,
a common runtime environment
and tools for creating new user interfaces
to traditional ZOS applications.
Programmers can develop and run traditional ZOS applications,
Unix applications and even ported windows applications
and Java and web server applications just to name a few.
A C++ compiler is also provided
to simplify the porting of applications to ZOS.
Another real benefit of running Unix applications on IBM Z
is that those applications can run
on the system Z integrated information processor or zip.
When configured with general purpose processes
within logical partitions running ZOS,
zips might help increase general purpose
processor productivity and might contribute
to lowering the overall cost of computing
for ZOS Java technology based applications
and some other Unix based workload like XML and CIM.
Zips are designed to operate asynchronously
with the general processes to execute Java programming
under control of the IBM Java virtual machine or JVM.
This can help reduce the demands
and capability requirements on general purpose processes
which might then be available
for reallocation to other IBM Z workloads.
So that's a wrap of this overview.
We're gonna get into much more detail
in the upcoming modules,
starting with a more thorough introduction to ZOS Unix.